Next stand alone session is Mr Deepak
Kumar Singal who is Managing Director &
PO from Hindustan Insurance Brokers.
Thank you.
Good
afternoon. First of all I am
grateful to Indian Express Group for giving an opportunity to a simple
villager like me to share
my life stock
insurance experience in front of all of you noble dignities.
We got our license as a
direct insurance broker in
2003. We were the first one to insure
electric vehicles in 2008. We are
electric and still managing the accounts
of many EV manufacturers
as for our life stock insurance
concern. It was never well that plan and
business strategy. I would call it a divine
intervention and Gods will be the
third generation connected with Badrinath and
Kedarnath
Temple and you know in 2013 there was a divine and
flood in Kedarnath killing more than 1000 people
and wiping out over 6500
people. Next year no we went there were absolutely
shocked to see the  I still remember the extent of damages
and the pain inflicted by such
floods. I spoke to so many
people and the discussions with my fellows. I still remember what he told me.
Babuji, my house was washed away, my family was
also gone. I had a horse, that also died.
Now I don't know what to do. It was really very moving. I felt very accomplished. I wondered
how I could bring about a change in the lives of these people.
From that day, my life took a new direction, a new
light, a new path, and it became my life's
mission: no
poor man's house should be destroyed because of the death of his animal; no
poor girl's marriage should be
stopped because of the death of her animal. The
Government of India's National Livestock
Mission has a scheme for animal insurance, which insures the
accidental and disease-related deaths of animals. The
budget is limited.
Implementation systems are still not
matched, but the scheme was there
and under that
scheme, in 2015, we insured 6000 animals in
Kedarnath under different and very difficult circumstances.
Circumstances harsh weather
and you will be surprised to know at that time
no use of technology was
made and there around 25000 animals in the
state of Uttarakhand and in whole of UP
only 8000 animals are insured then UP
invited us and we insured more than 2 lakh animals
in just five month
period then Haryana invited us and we
insured more than 4 lakh animals in a year
and you will be happy to know in one single
month we insured 64000
animals then we started in Jammu and
Kashmir we started in the month of July
2019 in Jammu and
Kashmir and you will know in August 2019 section
370 was removed there was
no internet transportation and
communications and were badly interrupted
but due to hard work of her team and the
support of government officials the scheme was a
success currently  We are working in the
states of Uttar Pradesh, Haryana, Uttarakhand,
Jammu Kashmir, Himachal Pradesh, Rajasthan, Jharkhand, Chhattisgarh,
Arunachal Pradesh
and going to two more states in North
East. I am very glad to share with you that this year we have
insured
1617 Mules in Amarnath by establishing
camps and it was really a very challenging thing
you know
to complete the process our team has to go in to
the field have to stay in camps
and we have to take a CID approval to be
on the route to Kedarnath it is not easy people are
not able to go and we established 17
camps and it was only possible because of the
dedication of the team and support of Lieutenant
Governor Mr. Manoj
Sinha. This year in Uttarakhand we have ensured
15800 Mules from 610 years back in
Kedarnath, Gangotri, Yamunotri and Hem
Saheb and if few of you have been there you
can  Understand the difficult circumstances,
live stock is a productive asset for
a
farmer and live stock is an integral
part of the dairy industry and you will be
surprised the dairy industry has got 4.5 percent
contribution to our GDP it employs more than
8 crore people and more over in rural
areas
again we have more than 50 crore live stock
in India and more than 30 crore out of them are
bovines bovines means cow and
buffalo then the question arises
and such a big ecosystem is there way
insurance of live stock is not even 1 percent of
the total population two two important
stakeholders in live
stock insurance one insurance company and
another
farmer there is no mutual trust between the two if you
understand the problem is of both, it is
from both sides, both have issues with each other let's
talk about the farmer the first question that
comes is it is very expensive
sir, when you get the insurance done it does not give the claim,
someone asks for a lot of papers, investigator
comes  He troubles us a lot, asks for money too, even if we
get the claim, it comes very late,
nobody listens,
now let's talk to the insurance company,
no, no brother, it's a moral hazard, we
insure a sick animal, it dies, the
unpatronable is replaced with an insured dead animal, they
fiddle and take the claim, there is
no market size at all, we waste our
time on this, it is
loss making, who will go to the village and work, from
where will we get the staff for claim settlement,
TPA services are not available in this,
if we look deeply then both the sides are
fine
and we have tried to single handedly
sort out these concerns at our level
from our own
resources, first of all, I did
not want to do this work, I also wanted to do it, so there was
negotiation with the brokerage also, we had to do this at any
cost, not initially and
spent so much money from our own pocket, just to go there
and do something for the
humanity, along with this I should also mention
National Life Stock Mission officials  He
appreciated our efforts a lot. Out of
10 issues that we took to the government, we heard only four out of 10. We heard only six. We
asked for 100 and were given only 50 but they did it. They always
respected our efforts. Whenever
we asked for time, we never got 15 days or a
week's time. We got time even on a two-hour notice. So
if we say that it is
impossible to change the system, it is
not impossible. It is a challenge. We have to come out of
it. Now we have made so many efforts. Regular meetings were held
with the government officials. Can we increase it a little? The
average subsidy was 60 per annum. Should we
reduce it or increase it to 85 per annum this
year onward?
Per an annum family was eligible for five animal
units. Now it is increased to 10 animal
units. The
family cooling period was 15 days.
Now it is increased to 21 days. Cooling period
means they insure an animal and it is done by
accident risk cover.  Immediate start and
it is applicable but it is done by sickness and
disease only after these many days you will get
the
claim so in this the first concern which
was of the beneficiary was expensive that has been sorted out to a large extent
of the insurance company which was of moral hazard, sick
animals are insured, in 21 days if the animal is
insured normally then
how will it penetrate by going to the village, earlier there were
no guidelines for brokers in this,
it is not an easy job for a broker to evolve in government business, many of my
friends understand this we have so many
representations to the
government and they this year finally put
clear cut guidelines for brokers in stock
mission live stock insurance
scheme the states invited us and positive but we
went on our own and face up to the task to
choose broker can work in fact we have been
harassed we have been thrown out we have been made all kinds
of
accusations  I was told at our face that I don't want you to break
like defense brokers
you will come and run away with the money and it was
so painful but it made our determination more difficult not only this many
processes are
blocked in the insurance process we
modified on our own first thing is the health
certificate which is signed by the doctor and then
another thing is the proposal form which is signed
by a beneficiary as all of us
no we started using a single document which was
health certificate [ __ ] proposal form
and we made it
numbered like a cover notebook it was not
legally a cover note but it was working as a
cover note in the system of the insurance
company and no jumping was allowed I give you an
example suppose a cover notebook and health
state book is for 25 leaves and we have got the
documents up to 20 leaves and then we go then our
system gets leave number 22 then we
Will ask where the leave number 21 is and if it is not there we want to
process leave number
22 Will ask the marketing person in the
field PS where the document number 20 is
and he says he has to send a cancelled
copy to us So
earlier says in government scheme where the
doctors all the doctors are implementing this
scheme after the death of an
animal they were issuing a health certificate in
the back date so that was a very big problem
and with this solution this problem was to a
great extent sorted
out we made it compulsory that every animal has to be
given four photographs for
every animal they have to give four
photographs of the live animal so we can
compare at the time of the death of the
animal we train our own man
power who can use our people who can use our people all the
documents have to be
sent to our office
digitally no physical document
delivery  Benefice Health Certificate
Beneficiary ID Details Beneficiary
Contribution Payment Receipt
and any other document if
required Currently we are having more than
5000 pcs
working in the field and you will be happy to know more than
10 per of them Our Pashu Sakhi
Women When a woman earns money in rural area it not only gives her
confidence it not only gives
additional income to the family it
improves overall ecosystem of the village and we have
seen the effect of this We talk from
insurance point of view the quality of work
by Pashu Sakhi is many times better than the male
members moreover integrity issue is to
the bare minimum and ethics and SO Ps are
followed very
properly We have developed our own
technology in our app we can download the
policy in the field we can see the process of
our claim where the claim is at the
moment field person can talk to  Our
executive is in the call center for any
query any grievance is there it can be
registered any queries are there you can do
chat also from here this was
the problem but in the field
no one from the insurance company responds no
one listens then
the data comes to our system our
processing center my team process the data
and we reject around 12 part of the data
received due to various reasons mainly we did
quality control here we process the data our
system is integrated with insurance
companies and state government and central
government till 12 o clock at night what ever
data we receive our system processes
people processes and by 8 o clock in the
morning message is send to
the beneficiary you can download the policy
and I think this is the fastest in live
stock
we got our own call center 24 hrs
all days it is open holi diwali wt
in corona disease it was working
Once an animal is found, you can call at our
call center and our call center can ask for the
photograph of the dead animal and verify whether it is the same animal or not. We send an
investigator to the
field. In plain areas, maximum one and a half hours. In hilly
areas including Jammu and Kashmir, Himachal, Arunachal,
Uttarakhand, maximum four hours. The
Government of India guidelines say they have to keep
the dead animal for up to 24
hours. We have trained the people from
investigators' team but there is no
investigator only. Surveyors have made
the investigators
and again they don't go into the feed them. There is no
manpower. We have to train them and this is a
regular process. There they come on
the line with us on video live. We can see the animal from all
angles again and more than 99
cases. We are clearing this is the genuine claim
and
firm and software gives all information about
MES.  Required by Government,
Central Government, State Government and other
departments apart from this, we give the
access to district level CDO at
our software, you can find out each and
every animal's details, owner's details, so
much work was done on paper, now note in
single piece leakage of government subsidy, there was moral
hazard in this scheme earlier as well as today, it is
not that moral hazard has ended
or our moral values ​​have changed,
you all can imagine how much time it will take to change
because
moral education has stopped being taught in our school,
we learnt from our experience that on a
particular festival
day, there used to be a lot of claims of sheep and goat
and it had been four-five years since we started working,
in a single day we were
flooded with the claims, so once we
experimented that sir, you
keep this animal and
its inspection will be done after 5 pm, in a single day we had 37
claims and this shock to learn out of  37 36
claim done in 1 hour
only one birth claim was left another very
big claim was snakebite
and earlier we had so many court
cases also because of snakebite
filing snakebite
case comes
under accidental insurance and no sick
animal and unproductive
animal is there to make a claim during
cooling period you have to show it is natural
death due to sickness it is death due to some
accidental cause and snakebite no
system was there and one more thing I would like to tell
you there is no system of post mortem of
animals everything is on paper they don't have
any theatres operation theatres for post mortem
and how will you carry the animal from one
place to another place in hilly areas and in
remote areas
and work lots on this try to find out how we
can certain than one very knowledgeable
doctor give us an advice you go for open
body post  Mad blood clotting water will be available
sorry blood
clotting by snake poisoning will be a
different kind of blood clotting and we
started open body post mortem and video
recording in the
last few years only to claim of snake
biting
enduring such huge population we are doing I am
surprised snakes have stopped biting
animals and all snakes from
Uttarakhand UP hilly area Jammu Kashmir
and Himachal have gun somewell same was
the case of
electric sir, in this I had
four buffaloes in the enclosure, a small wire was hung it got
electrocuted and we used to give claim,
then in this also some gentleman gave me knowledge
that what knowledge was given in this one day I
saw it myself, I was somewhere in Uttarakhand,
there was actually death due to electric shock,
it was a different case, all the hair on its body was
burnt and
there was a fire at the center power supply point, so to avoid any
dispute in this
we got open body post mortem done and again the
blood cutting was a different kind then we made it as
SOP and V
train surveyors  For this now for last two
years we have got no electricity
case and insurance companies are really
happy with this this
is a work related to poor people poor people always don't
know anything at the same
time I will say now village folks are very
smart they know about all schemes they have got all
remedy measures in minute they make complete
CM window and CM window
complaint we have to sort out in these days now we have got
separate section in our office just to
sort out the CM window
cases this was I got tired in 2017
I got call at the time in all hospitals of
Uttarakhand my number was pasted it still it is pasted but I don't get
call now
and sir the cow died and we have taken away the
tag it
might have been because it had ears earlier
before we used to cut its entire
ear and we stopped it only we
need tag it was big nonsense we told
you patwari  Talk to him and get the
Pradhan to write a letter along with it, get four
people as witnesses and send an investigator,
pay the claim but you will be surprised in the
next three months in more than 15
cases, cross took away the
tax and stop this claim,
you had given the money to that man, why didn't you give it to us, now at the
time Mr. Pankaj Khanna,
very dynamic officer, I saw that you do
n't act like much, same word, now what will you face, so
we manipulated it a little,
let me be very honest, we said that the
money which was deducted from the salary of the officer who had paid it, cannot be given now,
challenge you are doing a genuine job, that is a genuine
claim, but so many others,
apart from this, we
followed and developed some other systems from our experience, there are so many
smart people there, they will give some injection to the animal
and it will take 24 to 36 hours, it is a
dead
animal and after 36 hours it will rise again, so what should be done
for this
Then we developed some things like a
cotton ball is placed on its nose and it is
breathing very slowly, so it moves, if we fill a
bucket full of water and hit it with pressure then the animal will sneeze.
Personally I can
share another problem in animals
which is Gentleman Poultry, it suddenly bloats and swells like anything,
it is called Tiffany and its
intestine bursts because of some
infection in the intestine and it does give
in 12 hours to breathe and normally if it is a
Tiffany case the animal will die,
so many cases of Tiffany
come and it is natural but we have
seen in a particular belt of Haryana that
everyone is getting Tiffany, what is this, talk to the doctors,
no such disease is spread, there is
no such virus, proper FMD
vaccination has been done, nothing,
so we got into the same thing which we did earlier when we got an open body post mortem, let's get an
open
body post mortem done, it will be a
surprise on tomorrow for three  Cases in all three cases,
in all three cases, the intestine of the animal
was filled with jowar, jowar is a swarm and the
speciality of jowar is that you feed it one bucket of jowar and
four buckets of water, it will burst the intestine and the intestine will come
out of the
body, since then we have started doing open body
post mortem in these cases and since last
one month there is some peace,
this practical experience
cannot be gained by sitting here
and I myself we are running a good size
mid size insurance broking company
getting to many big corporates also but I
stop enjoying that my team looks
after and we have got very good accounts, many
good accounts of Bombay also we are
handling from Delhi
but it is going on as usual electric call, it is
going on as usual and it is a good
profitable business, my heart lies here, here we can
change the life of the people, we can bring
smile on the faces of the
people, all of you are talking about technology,
we are working on
technology we  We are trying to use
AI based models.
There is a technology called Muzzle technology.
Muzzle technology, just like we do it with Aadhaar, with
fingerprints. Similarly, there are
unique prints on the nose of bovine
and we are
trying to do it by pressing scan, using a photo. Till now, some
people say that their technology is under development and is
not 100% successful yet. Secondly, we cannot put it as
evidence in the court of law, but we are working on it and we are very sure it will be
a successful
technology. IIT Roorkee is working with us. Moreover, we are
working for this AI based
models with the University of
Delhi. Further, we are working on a new
platform where we will provide free medical
consultancy for animal health to animal
owners
and whatever we do with this platform, but this will be
for free in the times to come as well. If we can
save the animals, we can treat them
well at the right time. Animals will not die.
Insurance companies will be happy more than before.
That animal owner will be happy if you are
giving him a claim after three or four
months his income of four months is gone away another thing
you will be again surprised if there are four
animals tied in place and one animal
dies cow gets just half milk for next two
days they are shocked and I have seen the homes of so many poor people if an animal dies
food is not cooked in the house it is a
very painful
experience so we can save those animals it
is a great service to the nation to the
humanity another thing we are working on
with a new startup they have developed the in
testing phase motor bike mounted
laboratory such a big animal husbandry
department in every state huge budget but everything goes in salary very few
medicine
and people don't work of course
needless to say there are many
doctors who are dedicated there live to this cause
but to population they have very minimal
development lab  It is mounted on a motor
bike. The
bike can be taken to a village. They can take the
sample and give the testing report immediately. Because many
times we have seen problem of
calcium, you are treating for the iron in the animal.
So you put yourself at his place. You go to the
doctor. First thing you do is go for pathological
test. There is no pathological testing in animals
and if it works, it will make a very big
change this way. We are trying to provide
total solution by
coordinating with central and state
government for release of
subsidy. Talking to insurance company for the
integration of the
software. Delivery of all material such as
health certificate, books, tags, applicators,
publicity material at the village level is at our own
cost. We are not charging any charges but
no insurance company is ready to pay.
All marketing of the scheme, weather on TV
and radio, newspapers, pamphlets,
cameras, everything we are doing on our own. I said we are currently having more than
5000 pieces working with  Ass but believe me I have more than
pieces, you have 100 today, you will call 100 today only, we will
start work after noon, 25 will go away
and this is a regular
process, we have focused a lot on quality control,
still we are trying to improve by
processing the data, we also handle policy issues,
we sort out all the queries and grievances, we provide full support for the claims
of the investigator, when a person
goes and makes a file and sends it to our office,
we check that file also
in a particular sequence.  There are documents, if there is
any document or not, it is
not incomplete, we get that completed too,
so till the policy is in, there is no involvement of
insurance company, even in the claim, the file
is on the table of the Babu, it has just been done,
see, it is my habit, I can
speak till evening, Sanjay told me friend, he does
not keep quiet on this, whoever says cut it, the
file of short claim also goes in two ways,
we cannot recommend technically, but we
make a note on it, if it gets rejected,
close it with proof and if it is payable, then
we send it clean, then they just pay it, so everything we are doing is
accepting, making
the payment and receiving the premium in our
account. There is 5 crore rupees animal, if you
multiply it, then there is a market of minimum 500 crore rupees,
we are fighting here, be it motor,
corporate, client asks for money,
everyone is engaged in this, they are fighting for a piece of bread in the same, there is an
open market of 50 thousand crore rupees
in the village.  Dairy sector, if we
insure the animals, the death of the animals will be
saved, the loss due to the death of the animals will be
saved, so the people get de-
motivated, I have seen many people who brought
five cows, two of them died,
we closed the dairy, then the
confidence will come in them that if I incur loss,
I will bear the loss, now you see it is
4.5 but totally neglected dairy sector to
GDP, if it works, it can easily go to 6
to 7 per cent, more over income will go in the
hands of rural people, Hero Honda, Unilever
also sells, so when the supply is made in the villages,
then their
share increases, another thing is that when a villager
smiles, the money comes in the pocket of the city dweller,
from this point of view, if we
think that when India smiles, then India
's wealth increases, so we look from this
point of view, but we have to go in the
field, we need,
we have been working for so many years, we are
also going in the field, there are new challenges everyday, we
engage in new things  Yes, I am really thankful
to my family. First, my wife is a
professor of computer science at the
University of Delhi and at this particular
time, I would like to thank her personally.
I sacrifice my life for this cause.
Number one, I am particularly thankful
to the top management down to the line staff
of Oriental Insurance. I should not name any
company in particular here, but I would like to thank them
personally, Oriental Insurance
and New India Insurance, for the kind of
support they have given. Bahut baar mere bans bhi
ulte bareli ko ho gaye the, but the moment they gave
me support, they placed their hand on the shoulder. Arey chalo aa g humein, it
helped me. They motivated me at every moment.
But this dozen and here we need the support,
guidance, motivation, and company of
friends like you for this cause.
Now, I will stop with this, otherwise, they will switch
off the mic. My livestock is the wealth of the poor. The
livestock is the wealth of the poor. By giving livestock on the death of an animal, you
became the support of the poor. Thank you.